<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd in the cathedral church of St. Peter in York, on the 6th of February 1685/6 being the day on which His Majesty began his happy reign / by William Stainforth.</title>
            <author>Stainforth, William, d. 1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28875</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10772242</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10772242</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45788</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61246)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45788)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1410:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd in the cathedral church of St. Peter in York, on the 6th of February 1685/6 being the day on which His Majesty began his happy reign / by William Stainforth.</title>
                  <author>Stainforth, William, d. 1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jo. White, for Francis Hildyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Imprimatur R. Altham, Rmo. P. Dno. Johan. Archiep. Ebor. à sacris domesticis."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXIV, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45788:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preach'd in the Cathedral Church OF <hi>St. Peter in York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the <hi>6th.</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> 1685/6. Being the Day on which His <hi>MAJESTY</hi> began his Happy <hi>Reign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM STAINFORTH</hi> Reſidentiary <hi>Canon</hi> of <hi>YORK.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Ro. Altham,</hi> Rmo P. Dno. <hi>Johan.</hi> Archiep. <hi>Ebor.</hi> à ſacris Domeſticis.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>YORK,</hi> Printed by <hi>Jo. White,</hi> for <hi>FRANCIS HILDYARD</hi> Bookſeller, at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Stonegate,</hi> Anno Dom. M. DC. LXXXVI.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45788:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45788:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable SIR THOMAS SLINGSBY BARONET.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Humbly Preſent you with a <hi>Sermon,</hi> which when it was preach'd, met with ſuch a favourable reception and kind entertainment from ſome of the Loyal and Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Auditors, that they look'd upon the Printing it to be of public <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Advantage, becauſe it might (as they thought) in ſome meaſure at leaſt contribute to the Redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch of His <hi>Majeſty's</hi> Subjects as have been miſled into ſeditious Practices, and prevent others from falling into the ſnares of the ſame accurſed Seduction; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they importun'd me to make it as Publick as now it appears. And tho' I took ſome time to conſider before I would yield to their Requeſts, yet when I had once reſolved to comply with them, I found no place for Deliberation to whom I ſhould Dedicate it, or whoſe Name I ſhould bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to give countenance and protection to it. For the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of this <hi>Sermon,</hi> being to promote an holy Fear of God, and a loyal Fear of the King, no Perſon did, or indeed could occur to my thoughts, whoſe Patronage could be more proper
<pb facs="tcp:45788:3"/> or uſeful to a Diſcourſe of this nature, than your own; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe You, <hi>Sir,</hi> are ſo great an Example of thoſe two neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and indiſpenſible Duties which are here recommended. Your holy fear of God has been made viſible to all who know you, in your conſtant unalterable Perſeverance in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> and in your zealous Concernment, which upon all juſt Occaſions you expreſs, for its true Intereſts, and unalienable Privileges, notwithſtanding all the Temptations you may have met with either at Home or Abroad, to corrupt your holy Faith and miſguide your devout Affections. Your loyal fear of the King has been as evident as the former throughout the whole courſe of your Converſation, and moſt vigorouſly exerted and diſcover'd it ſelf in ſutable Effects and a Loyal Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour under the moſt frightful Poſture, and diſcouraging Circumſtances of public Affairs, when ſome were driven from their Duty and Allegiance by diſmal Stories, and factious Amuſements, and others were wheadl'd out of it by popular Addreſſes, and ſmooth and crafty Inſinuations. And therefore, you juſtly enjoy not only the Eſtate and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Titles which belong'd to your Anceſtors, but alſo all that public Eſteem and Reputation with your Prince and Country, which their fam'd and celebrated Loyalty procur'd for them. I need go no higher for a Proof of this than to your immediat Progenitor and Honourable Father <hi>Sir HENRY SLINGSBY,</hi> who perſever'd in his Allegiance to his Prince, to ſuch a degree of Faithfulneſs, as made him Reſiſt even unto Bloud (not in a Fanatical but Chriſtian ſence) and
<pb facs="tcp:45788:3"/> lay down his Life for his Natural tho' baniſhed Soveraign, whom no Terrours or Allurements of a remorſeleſs and craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper could oblige him to renounce. So that Loyalty ſeems entail'd upon your Family, and looks as if it were your Inheritance as well as your Choice, convey'd in your Bloud as well as infus'd at your Baptiſm, and deſcended upon you by your natural as well as ſpiritual Birth. But however, it is impoſſible that you ſhould ever depart from your ſelf or your Duty, while you live in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and make her Rules the Meaſures of your Subjection; for ſhe teacheth a perfect, abſolute, unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Subjection, by teaching all her Members to Obey all the juſt and lawful Commands of their King, and with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and reſignation to ſuffer his Cenſures and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, where they cannot obey. And I do not doubt, but one great Reaſon among all the reſt, why you value and live in the Church of <hi>England</hi> rather than in any other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Society whatſover, is becauſe her Doctrine and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, in point of civil Subjection, are ſo conformable to thoſe of our Bleſſed Saviour, and his holy Apoſtles, who died rather than they would reſiſt thoſe Soveraign Powers they liv'd under, and who have forbidden all Reſiſtance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pain of eternal Damnation. And may you long live in the Communion of this Holy Church, to do Honour to God, and Service to your Prince upon Earth; and God out of his infinit Mercy in his due time receive you into the Church Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant in Heaven. This is and ſhall be the conſtant daily Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt obliged and moſt humble Servant <hi>WILLIAM STAINFORTH.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45788:4"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45788:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Prov. 24. 21.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſon, fear thou the Lord and the King, and medle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>CIvil Government is the great Comprehenſive Wordly bleſſing; for it is the Foundation of Peace and Quiet, the Spring and Fountain of all thoſe Ineſtimable Advantages which adorn and felicitate Humane Societies. For without Government there would be nothing but Wildnes and Confuſion, Rapine and Violence, and all the bloody Outrages of a barbarous and Merciles Inhumanity. And therefore God, who deſign'd the Happineſs of man in his Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not only implanted in his Nature ſtrong and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Inſtincts after Society, but alſo took care that he might Enjoy all the intended Bleſſings and deſign'd ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Society by inſtituting Government for its Support and preſervation. This is plain from that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Dominion which God gave <hi>Adam</hi> over his Wife and all his Natural Deſcendents, by vertue of which every man, who was born into the World was born in a State of ſubjection, and Ow'd Duty and Obedience to him, from whom under God he derived his Natural Being. So that Government began by the Divine Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as ſoon as there were any capable Objects for its Exerciſe and adminiſtration, it being founded in Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45788:5"/> Authority, which as Families increaſed and multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, grew up to the height and largenes of Imperial and Political Power.</p>
            <p>Now of all the Kinds and Forms of Government, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy is not only the moſt Primitive and Natural, but the moſt Compleat and Perfect; for as it is moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Heavenly Pattern, and nearlieſt reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the Government of God, So it is moſt Conducive to all thoſe Uſeful and Beneficial purpoſes, for which men enter into Societies and for which Government was inſtituted. This might be prov'd by ſhewing, that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy has all thoſe real advantages, which any other Forms of Government can pretend unto, without being ſubject to many of thoſe Numerous Inconveniences and Miſchiefs which inſeparably attend them.</p>
            <p>And of Monarchies, that which is limited and Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary deſerves the preference for its ſingular Value &amp; Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes. Now by a Limited Monarchy I mean ſuch an One, where the Supream and Unaccountable Power of the Prince, as to its exerciſe and adminiſtration, is under the direction of ſtated and fixed Rules (whether Poſitive Laws or Immemorial Cuſtoms) which by a long Train of Experiences have been found to be Juſt and Equal, and advantagious to the public welfare of the whole Community, and which the King is under all the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of Honour, Intereſt and Conſcience to defend and maintain. In ſuch a Caſe the People know what they have to truſt unto and depend upon, and as they are thereby ſecur'd from all the ſervile fears of an abitrary Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45788:5"/> ſo they have the moſt powerful Motives even of this World, to pay a cheerful Obedience to the King, and to live peaceably and quietly under his Government.</p>
            <p>By an Hereditary Monarchy I underſtand ſuch an one, where the Right of Succeſſion is founded in Proximity of Bloud, and derived by a Lineal-deſcent to the next a Kin. And as there is uſually more reaſon to think that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Royal Race and Extraction are more fitted by their Birth and Education, by their Natural Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and acquir'd Abilities for Empire and Government than others of Ignoble Bloud, and mean Breeding, ſo by ſuch a continued and uninterrupted way of Succeſſion all Vacuums and Interregnums in the Government, and all the Broils, and Miſchiefs, and Confuſions which ariſe from Factious Competitions and ſtrivings in popular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, are prevented. Now it is our Happineſs, that we live under a Government thus Qualified and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, where the King never Dies, but is immortal in an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Succeſſion; and where the People enjoy all the Property and Freedom which they can hope for, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to themſelves from any Government whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And therefore with what Joy and Gratitude, with what Praiſes &amp; Devotion ought we to celebrate this Day, whereon God was pleas'd to advance our Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign to the Throne of his Royal Anceſtours, and notwithſtanding the popular Diſtempers of the Age, and the turbulent Deſigns of Factious Men, to ſettle Him in a quiet and peaceful Poſſeſſion of his Natural and Legal Inheritance. This was an infinit Mercy, a Mercy to which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45788:6"/> we owe our lives, our Peace and the Preſervation of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is Dear and Valuable to us. May this Mercy ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſlip our of our Minds! May we always remember it ſo as to be truly and ſincerely thankful for it! May we alwayes expreſs our unfeigned Thankfulneſs by all the proper and juſt returns of an humble and faithful Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which we owe to God and his Vicegerent. And that we may be perſwaded to do this, I have made choice of theſe words of <hi>Solomen</hi> for the Subject of my preſent Diſcourſe, <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and medle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the former Part of this Text we have the Duties which we owe to God and the King enjoyn'd; and both theſe Duties are expreſs'd by one and the ſame word <hi>Fear: Fear thou the Lord and the King.</hi> In the latter part of it we have an uſeful expedient, or a proper means recommended and preſcrib'd for ſecuring and preſerving us in our Duty, <hi>medle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We have the Duties which we owe God and the King enjoyn'd us, and both of them expreſs'd by one and the ſame Word <hi>Fear.</hi> Now Fear ſtrictly and Philoſophically taken, is that Paſſion or affection of mind, which is wrought and ſtirr'd up in us through the apprehenſion of ſome Evil or Harm, which Threatens us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> And what can ſo reaſonably excite and awaken this Paſſion in us, as a ſerious and impartial Conſideration of God, who in his Nature is infinitely juſt, and infinitely powerful? for as he is infinitely juſt, we are thereby aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd that he is always diſpos'd and inclin'd to puniſh all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45788:6"/> thoſe, who maliciouſly and wilfully offend againſt the Holy and righteous Laws of his Government; and as He is infinitely powerful, we are thereby aſſur'd that nothing can reſiſt the Inflictions of his Wrath, or oppoſe the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of his Vengeance, but He can puniſh and torment any or all his Creatures tho' united in an univerſal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy and Rebellion againſt his Authority, in what kind, and to what degree, and to what duration He pleaſeth. So that theſe things conſider'd, we have infinitely more cauſe to fear God than all other Beings, which make and fill the Univerſe; for how can any thing be ſuch a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Being, or ſuch an affecting Object of our Fear as God, when there is nothing but Himſelf Almighty and Irreſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible in Power? This plainly ſhews, that God can as far out do all other Beings in the Ills and Miſchiefs which He can bring upon us, as He exceeds them in the meaſure &amp; extent of that Power with which He is inveſted. And alas! what proportion is there betwixt the Power of God, and that of his Creatures? for the power of the Creature is limited and confin'd, and as it is always under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul of God, and ſubject to thoſe reſtraints, which He ſhall at any time pleaſe to put upon it, ſo in its freeſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, it cannot go beyond thoſe fixed Bounds, which are ſet to its Nature, and determine the extent of it. But the Power of God is immeaſurable and irreſiſtible, and nothing but his own Will can reſtrain the meaſure of its Actings, or ſet any bounds to the Exerciſe and Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it. It extends it ſelf to all things poſſible, &amp; beyond that nothing can be conceiv'd as nothing can be done.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45788:7"/>
            <p> Thus you ſee what grounds there are for our Fear of God and what Stupid and Unthinking creatures we muſt be, if our minds are not affected with an awful ſenſe and dreadful apprehenſion of his infinit Power and Majeſty. And certain it is, that if the Fear of God was duly eſtabliſhed and fixed in our hearts, It would prove a pregnant &amp; fruitful Principle of all manner of Piety and goodnes and would have an influence upon our external &amp; viſible Actions proportionable to the reception &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment which it found in our minds: It would render us infinitely Cautious and Watchful over our thoughts and words and actions, and make us take all conceivable and poſſible Care that we might do nothing which might be diſpleaſing and offenſive to God: It would pull down Our haughty Spirits and bend our ſtiff necks, and make every thing in us Bow and Stoop to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority and readily comply with all the Known Expreſſes and Declarations of it. It would make us approach the Divine Preſence with a becoming Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and behave our ſelves in it with ſuch Seriouſneſs and Humility and Devotion, as is ſuitable to the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and Majeſty of that Infinite Being to whom we make our addreſſes: It would make us Honour every thing which has any peculiar relation to God, and put a difference betwixt what is Sacred (whether Perſons or Things) &amp; what is common by ſuch particular Reſpects as are expreſſive of their Holy Singularity and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priation. In a word, If we really feared God and lived under an awful Senſe of his Being, we ſhould no more
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45788:7"/> dare to provoke his Almighty Juſtice by breaking any of his Known Laws than we ſhould be willing to be Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally miſerable. And for this very reaſon the Fear of God is ſo frequently injoyn'd us in the Holy Scriptures; &amp; for this very reaſon the Fear of God is oftentimes put for the whole Sum of Religion, and for all that Worſhip and Duty which we Ow to God; for whereſoever it is truly grounded and deeply rooted, all the other parts of Holines and Righteouſnes will flow from it as from their Natural and proper Principle. For it is impoſſible for any man to be affected with it, and not feel the force and efficacy of its nature in a perfect ſubjection of his heart and an entire reſignation of his Will to the commands and diſpoſal of God Almighty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As we are Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ded to fear God, ſo alſo to fear the King, and tho there is not an equal Reaſon, yet there is a ſufficient one for ſo doing. For the King is Gods Vicegerent and Repreſentative, and is intruſted by him with the Temporal Power and Material Sword for the ſupport of his Authority and Vindication of his Government. God, who has ſet him upon his Throne for the Good of the whole Community, has furniſhed him with all thoſe means which are neceſſary for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of ſuch an excellent end. For He has not only given him Authority to Enact and preſcribe Lawes for the Regulation of his Subjects, but alſo Power to inflict Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties upon ſuch as dare to tranſgreſs them. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed without ſuch a Power of Coercion all his other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority would prove lame and defective and inſufficient
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45788:8"/> for all thoſe purpoſes for which it is Ordain'd. For the Generallity of Mankind are not ſo ingenuous as to be wrought upon by rational arguments &amp; wiſe diſcourſes, nor to conform to the moſt prudent &amp; uſeful Rules upon the bare propoſals of Authority; There muſt be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to work upon their Fears as wel as to Convince their Underſtandings, before they will learn or practiſe the Duty of Subjection. And though the great &amp; ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble advantages of Order &amp; Government are ſufficient Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to engage any thoughtful and conſidering Perſon to Civil Obedience and a regular Submiſſion to public Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, yet few men conſider what is their true Intereſt, or wherein their greateſt Happineſs conſiſts, or what are the beſt and moſt proper means to attain and ſecure it, but live incogitantly &amp; careleſly without any other thoughts or reflections, but what their impotent Paſſions and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly appetites inſpire them with. And therefore it is no wonder, that men generally are ſo turbulent and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in their natures and Inclinations, and upon every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation &amp; diſguſt, nay upon every fooliſh Caprice &amp; Humour ſo ready to combine in factious deſigns and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in rebellious enterprizes, and to pull Ruin upon themſelves by offering Violence to the Government. But as this ſhews the Folly &amp; madnes of ſuch People, &amp; how little they underſtand either their Duty or their Happines, So it demonſtratively proves the Neceſſity of a Right to puniſh offenders, &amp; of a Force ſufficient to execute that Right, in all thoſe who are inveſted with Supream Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Authority. For tho' men will not be won to live
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45788:8"/> dutifully and Loyally by the charms of Peace and the Bleſſings of Obedience, yet they may be conſtrained and forc'd to do ſo by the Dreads and Terrors of Public Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Fear of Puniſhment will have its effects upon ſuch Obſtinate and unruly Tempers, whom the Hopes of rewards can make no impreſſions upon. For thoſe men who through ſtupidity and dulneſs, through Ignorance or Inconſideration have no affecting and lively ſenſe of true Happines, and Conſequently are not to be mov'd by the propoſals &amp; aſſurances of it to Keep within the bounds &amp; limits of their Duty, yet cannot hinder themſelves from being ſenſible of Pain and Torment, nor ſo far harden &amp; fortifie their Natures againſt the impreſſions of Fear, as not to feel the force and Power of that Paſſion, when they lye under the apprehenſion of Impendent Ruine or approaching Miſery. And therefore as men naturally endeavour to avoid what they fear, ſo it is neceſſary that the public Magiſtrate ſhould be armed with ſuch an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as may create Fear in all thoſe who otherwiſe might be diſpoſ'd to reſiſt and riſe up againſt Him, that ſo He may conſtrain thoſe by the Terrors of His Juſtice, whom the effects of His Love, Clemency &amp; Bounty could not Oblige to be Subject. And accordingly that men might want no Motives to be Subject to Government, God has arm'd Kings with an Authority to Threaten Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments and a Power to inflict them.</p>
            <p>So St. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth us, when he tells us that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>beareth not the ſword in vain, for He is the Miniſter of God, a Revenger to execute wrath on them that do evil,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45788:9"/> And this ſhews, that as we have reaſon to fear God, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to fear the King, tho' not in the ſame degree and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion. Tho' the King cannot make us miſerable to that degree which God can do, becauſe his Power is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and cannot reach us beyond this Life, yet He has Power to make us ſo far miſerable as juſtly renders him an Object of Dread and Terrour to us. For if we are unruly and diſobedient, and will not be kept within the compaſs of our Duty, He has Power and Authority to do Juſtice upon us, and inflict ſuch Puniſhments as are proportionable to the Nature of our Guilts and agreeable to the Preſcription of the public Laws. In ſome Caſes He can put Marks of public Infamy and diſgrace upon us: In others he can puniſh us in our Eſtates by ſetting pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niary mulcts upon us: In others he can add a further pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to that, and afflict us in our Bodies aſwell as in our Purſes: In others, where the Offence is capital, as all Treaſon and Rebellion is, He can Taint our Blood, and Confiſcate our Eſtates, and put us to Death.</p>
            <p>So that, if we did but fear the King proportionably to the Evils which he can bring upon us, we ſhould not dare to provoke his wrath, by offending againſt his Laws: we ſhould not dare to combine and Conſpire againſt his Royal Authority, nor move one Step which has any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Tendency either to deſtroy his Sacred Perſon, or endanger the diſſolution of his Government. And I do not doubt, if the ſtouteſt and hardieſt Rebel of them all (always excepting thoſe who are Rebels out of Principle and Conſcience) did but frequently and ſeriouſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>k
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45788:9"/> upon the Ax and Gibbet, and that infamous and untime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Death, which is always the deſert, and commonly is the Fate of Rebels, (I ſay) I do not doubt, but theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections would ſo awaken their Fears, as to Quell their Seditious Purpoſes, and put a ſtop to their Factious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and ſuggeſt unto them ſuch wiſe and prudent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, as would keep them Peaceable and Loyal under the beſt of Monarchies, and the beſt of Governments. And for this very Reaſon the Fear of the King is commanded and injoyn'd us, as if it were the whole of that Duty and Allegiance which we owe unto him.</p>
            <p>Thus having Diſcourſt in ſhort upon thoſe Duties of Fear which we owe to God and the King, I proceed to make ſuch Obſervations as may be gathered both from the Connexion of the Words, and the Order of them.</p>
            <p>1. We may Obſerve, that Religion and Loyalty have ſuch a cloſe dependence, and ſtrict connexion with each other, that the wiſe Man puts them both together and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns them upon us in ſuch a manner, as if they were but one ſingle indiviſible Duty. And certain it is, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſome men may ſeparate them in their internal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions, or external profeſſions, yet in truth and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity they are always link'd and conjoin'd, and inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly accompany each other. And this I ſhall make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by ſhewing</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That no man can be truly Religious who is not a Loyal Subject.</item>
               <item>2. That no man can be ſtedily and immoveably Loyal, who is not truly and ſincerely Religious.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:45788:10"/> 1. No man can be truly Religious who is not a Loyal Subject. For what Duty is more clearly and ſtrongly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd upon us by the Laws of our holy Religion than this of Obedience and Subjection to Kings and Princes? Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is God's Ordinance, and Kings are his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents, deputed by his Authority, and Arm'd with his Power to keep the World in Order, Peace and Quietneſs. And that they may be ſecure in their Thrones and invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable in their Perſons, and irreſiſtible in their Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, God has plainly taught us by the Light of Nature, and the Revelation of his Word, always to bear in our minds ſuch awful regards, &amp; to expreſs in our Carriage ſuch dutiful Reſpects as are ſuitable to the Excellency of their Character, the Dignity of their Office, and the Uſefulneſs of their Inſtitution. How numerous are the Texts which might be produc'd out of the Old and New Teſtaments to this purpoſe, wherein the Divine Original of Kingly Power is clearly aſſerted, a willing Obedience to all their juſt and lawful Commands is indiſpenſibly injoyn'd, and all manner of Hoſtile and Forcible Reſiſtance either of their Perſons, or their Authority, is expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and ſeverely threatned? ſo that if the Truth of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is to be judg'd by thoſe Rules of Duty which God himſelf has deliver'd, and if we are not to be reckon'd any further Religious than as we ſincerely conform to thoſe Rules, it is plain, that a Religious Rebel is as groſs and palpable a Contradiction as a Sovereign Unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Subject, and it is in effect to ſay, that a man lives under the Directions of God's Commands whilſt he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45788:10"/> the plaineſt Intimations, and violates the cleareſt Injunctions of the Divine Will.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied that many have rebell'd out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and taken up Arms againſt their Natural and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Prince from an accurſed Perſuaſion, that they were not only allow'd but bound by the Laws of God to do ſo. But as the Nature of things are ſtated and determined, fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and permanent, and do not alter and vary with mens Opinions and Apprehenſions about them; ſo no Errors and Miſtakes of ours about Religion can either turn that into a real Truth which is a certain falſhood, or convert that into a neceſſary Duty of Chriſtianity, which either in it ſelf, or in its conſequence is an effectual Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any of its Precepts. Now all Reſiſtance of the Supreme Sovereign Power is plainly forbidden by the Laws of our common Chriſtianity, and therefore Reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance will ever be a ſin, tho' we are never ſo ſtrongly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of its being a Duty, and for the ſame reaſon we ſhall always be ſo far Rebels againſt God, as we are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels againſt the King.</p>
            <p>And tho' it be true, that a Conſcientious Rebel is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much to be Pitied, becauſe what he does may be ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more to the Power of his Errour, than to the Malice of his Will, yet of all Rebels theſe are the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the State and Government: For he who is a Rebel out of Conſcience is puſh'd on to his wickedneſs, &amp; encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd to perſevere in it by the moſt Powerful Motives, which can influence &amp; affect humane Nature. For he who is perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that his Sin is his Duty, muſt needs look upon himſelf
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45788:11"/> Oblig'd by the Authority of God himſelf to Commit it, and has all thoſe great and glorious rewards, which are promis'd to any Chriſtian and Vertuous undertaking, to encourage and animate him to the practiſe of the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious Villany. And therefore the Supream Power can never be too watchful over the Motions, nor keep too ſtrict a hand over the Men of ſuch Principles, whoſe Faith is Faction, whoſe Religion is Rebellion, becauſe nothing but a perfect Diſability and want of Power in them can ever reſtrain their Wild and furious Zeal from making Attempts upon the Government and creating diſorders in it. Theſe are ſo many Snakes and Vipers in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the State, which whileſt they are cheriſh'd with its Warmth and kindly influences are alwayes endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Sting it to death, and to Eat out the very heart and vitals of its Conſtitution, and no Truſt or Confidence can reaſonably be repoſed in them, until they abandon their factious Principles and be Converted to the Truth and the Government by a full and ſincere Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of their Duty.</p>
            <p>An Atheiſtical Rebel, may be held from purſuing his factious deſigns by the Viſible terrors of the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, Or he may be won over to the Government by thoſe ſecular advantages which his peaceable Compliance with the preſent eſtabliſhment may procure for him. Or a Man who is a Rebel againſt his Principle aſwel as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Prince may conſider his Folly and his Guilt and repent of it. His Conſcience may awaken and recover it ſelf, and arreſt him with its dreadful convictions, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45788:11"/> by ſhewing him the black Impiety and inevitable danger of his Seditious proceedings bring him back to himſelf and to his Duty, and beget in him firm and invincible reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of being faithful to his Conſcience and to his Prince, and of never departing any more from the Fidelity and Allegiance which is due to both of them. But there are no grounds for conceiving any ſuch hopes of a Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Rebel; for he is under the poſſeſſion and Conduct of a Principle, which is too ſtrong and powerful for any Earthly Motives or Secular Conſiderations; and all thoſe Ingagements to Loyalty and Civil Subjection which have relation to another Life, through the Malignity of his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror &amp; the Corruptions of his conſcience are made to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to his Rebellious purpoſes, and to cheriſh &amp; Encourage him in his moſt Furious &amp; Zealous executions of them. So that nothing but perfect deſpair &amp; an abſolute Incapacity of Harming the Government, can ever withhold a Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Rebel from diſturbing the Peace and endeavouring the Subverſion of it. And therefore nothing can be more Reaſonable in it ſelf, nor Uſeful to the Public, nor Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in our Governours, then to take all due care, that thoſe may never have any means nor opportunities of Embroiling the Quiet and ſhaking the Foundation of the Government, who look upon it as a point of Conſcience and as a part of Religion to be alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd and alwayes reſolved to endeavour the Confuſion and Deſtruction of it.</p>
            <p>But what Monſtrous Illuſions and Diabolical Infatuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt they ly under, who think Reſiſtance of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45788:12"/> Power in any caſe or upon any account whatſoever to be a Duty of Chriſtianity, or the Dictate of an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened Conſcience! Who perſwade themſelves that they are obedient to the Impulſes of Gods Spirit in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the Authority of His Vicegerent, and are promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Honour of his Government in pulling down the Ordinances of his Providence! For ſuch are Kings, who are ſet upon their Thrones by Gods Authority and appointment, and in an eſpecial manner bear the Impreſs and Character of his Divinity upon them, For God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tells us, <hi>That by him Kings Reign,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is no Power but of God, and the Powers that be, are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>ordain'd of God,</hi> and that the Supreme Magiſtrate <hi>is the Miniſter of God;</hi> and that no Reſiſtance may be made to his Authority nor any Violence offer'd to his Perſon, He tells us, <hi>That we muſt be Subject to him not only for wrath but Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>that they who reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi> And the Example of Our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour and the Behaviour of his Holy Apoſtles, and the Practice of the Primitive Chriſtians were confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to this Doctrine; for they never diſputed the Lawful Commands of their Governours, Nor deny'd active Obedience to their Prince, when it was conſiſtent with the indiſpenſible Duty which they Ow'd to God. And when the Commands of their Prince were unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and unjuſt, and could not be complied with, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violating their Conſciences, and offending God, they neither open'd their Mouths in derogation of his Honour, nor lifted up their hands in defiance of his Authority, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45788:12"/> with an admirable mixture of Meekneſs, and Patience, and Charity, ſuffer'd when they could not obey, and bore the Puniſhment which was inflicted. And they who give any other Accounts of the Doctrines of true Chriſtianity, or of the Practices of its Primitive and Orthodox Profeſſors, do fouly miſrepreſent the one, and injuriouſly bely the other, and are as malicious Enemies to the Honour and Intereſt of our common Chriſtianity, as they are to the civil Authority of Soveraign Princes. For Chriſtianity is not only the moſt <hi>Pure,</hi> but the moſt <hi>Peaceable</hi> and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Inſtitution which ever was ſet on foot in the World; It guards the Thrones, and ſecures the Perſons, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the Authority of Princes with ſuch ſtrong and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Defenſatives, that no man can break through them but at the utmoſt peril of his Immortal Soul, nor without incurring the Penalty of eternal Damnation. And therefore every man ceaſeth to be a Chriſtian, when he commenceth Rebel, renounceth the Croſs of Chriſt when he ſets up a Standard againſt his Prince, and has as little of true Religion as he has of Chriſtian Loyalty in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. No man can be ſtedily and immoveably Loyal who is not truly Religious. And this muſt needs be ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no men but ſuch as are truly Religious, are govern'd by a Principle, which prompts them to a conſtant invari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Uniformity of dutiful Reſpect and Loyal behaviour towards their lawful Sovereign.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Atheiſt</hi> who denies the Being of a God, and a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Perſon, who lives without any fear of his Power, or regard to his Laws, are equally under the Dominion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45788:13"/> of Senſe, and the Government of its Appetites, and are only ſwai'd by ſuch Conſiderations as have reſpect to their temporal and Earthly Felicity. Their Heaven is upon Earth, and they neither look nor wiſh for any other Joys than what ariſe from the Indulgence and Gratification of their ſenſual Affections. So that ſuch men can have no other Motives to be Loyal, than what the preſent Intereſts of this Life furniſh them with. For the conſiderations of God and Religion being laid aſide there remains nothing but the good things of this World to affect them with, and determine their Reſolutions; and therefore ſuch men cannot be Loyal any further, than the Hopes and Fears of this World will give them leave to be ſo. Indeed it cannot be denied becauſe it is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of undoubted Experience, that many Prophane and Immoral men have behav'd themſelves with great Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Spirit and Conſtancy of Reſolution in the Service of their Prince, Follow'd him in all the changes and revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of his fortunes, ſtuck by him in his Extremeſt Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities and worſt Condition and expos'd their Lives and Fortunes to the Utmoſt hazards for the defence of his Perſon and preſervation of his Government. But what of all this? the Evidence of this Experience and the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of this Fact does neither deſtroy the truth of this Poſition, nor rebate the force of my reaſoning about it. For if all this Loyal behaviour did not proceed from an affecting ſenſe of that Duty which we Owe to God, nor from a Conſcientious regard which we ought to have for all his Inſtitutions, If it was not the effect of a vertuous choice, the reſult of pious and Religious conſiderations,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45788:13"/> It can be aſcrib'd to nothing but a caſual &amp; contingent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, ſuch a Principle as might indifferently have made them falſe Traytors, or faithful Subjects, and conſequently their Loyalty was not ſo much their Vertue as their good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. And therefore I think it no wonder at all, that ſome men who gave great Proofs of an Unſhaken Conſtancy, and invincible Courage in the Cauſe of our late Royal Martyr, ſhould deſert their former Profeſſions, and in ſome late jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Affairs give ſhrewd ſuſpitions of a turbulent and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Spirit, of malicious and ſpightful Deſigns againſt the Perſon and Authority of their Prince. For all this may be eaſily ſuppoſed and accounted for, without ſuppoſing any change in the Men: The men &amp; their Principles may be the ſame that ever they were, and though they exert and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves in different and contrary Effects, yet this contrariety of Appearance and Operation is conſiſtent with the influence and efficacy of the ſame Numerical Principle which works contrarily according to the change of Seaſons, and the Alteration of Affairs, and the Variation of their ſecular Intereſts and the different Apprehenſions, which they may have of the moſt likely Means to promote and ſecure them. Formerly they might think it their only In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to uphold Monarchy and defend its Inſeparable and undoubted Rights, againſt all the Rebellious Invaders of it; and this Conſideration might reaſonably enough in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage them on the King's Side, and keep them cloſe &amp; Firm to his Party. But of late they might alter their Thoughts as to the moſt probable Methods, both of preſerving and improving their ſecular Intereſts, and perſwade themſelves, that there was no ſuch likely way, both to ſave their own
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45788:14"/> Stakes, &amp; win thoſe of others, as by unſettling the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and overturning its fundamental Conſtitutions; and what difficulty can there be in believing that the ſame Principle which formerly made them Loyal, ſhould under ſuch Circumſtances intoxicate them with the Spirit and Frenzy of Sedition, and ingage them in ſuch licentious Courſes as apparently tended to the Ruine of the King, and the Deſtruction of his Government? Alas! nothing can be more clear and evident from the Nature of the thing, than that a man, who is a mere Politician, and whoſe only Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple is worldly Intereſt, and who governs all his Actions by ſuch Maxims and Rules, as that ſuggeſts unto him, can never be faithful to any Party whatſoever any longer than he Judges it to make for his Intereſt to be ſo; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he obſerves his Intereſt to lie another way than in that in which he has already proceeded, the Principle by which he is guided, will oblige him to take new Meaſures, and put on quite different appearances, to change ſides, and act directly contrary to his former undertakings.</p>
            <p>But now a Man who is inſpir'd with the Spirit of true Chriſtianity, who underſtands his Duty to his Prince, as it is taught and laid down by his Bleſſed Saviour, and is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to practice according to thoſe Meaſures and Rules of Subjection, which the Goſpel has Eſtabliſhed; ſuch a man can never be any other thing than the moſt faithful and loyal Subject in the World. For as the Rule by which he is guided, will not allow of any thing upon any account whatſoever, which is either inconſiſtent with the true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or deſtructive of the juſt Authory of his Prince, ſo the Principle by which he is acted, will not ſuffer him to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45788:14"/> decline from his Rule, but when all other Motives fail, which are of an inferior and worldly Conſideration, this alone will keep him firm and cloſe to his Duty. For as the Goſpel is his Rule, ſo Conſcience is his Principle; and as the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of His Rule do not rely upon any Humane Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſo the Force of his Principle does not depend upon any earthly Reſpects, but derives its Power and Efficacy from the inviolable Authority of God, and thoſe infinit Motives of eternal Bliſs, and eternal Miſery, upon which God has Eſtabliſhed his Laws, and enforced their Obſervation. And therefore a Man, who is loyal for Conſcience ſake, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Chriſtian Principles, will always be true and faithful to his Prince, however things go in the World: His Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty is built upon a Rock, an immoveable Foundation, which can neither be undermin'd or ſhaken by any Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents or Changes whatſoever.</p>
            <p>2. We may obſerve from the Order of the Words, that tho we are to fear both God and the King, yet we are in the firſt place to fear God, and then the King. God is the prime and principal Object of our awful Regards, and after Him Kings are to be reverenc'd by us. And indeed there is the ſame Reaſon why we ſhould fear God before Kings, that there is vvhy vve ſhould fear him at all. And this I ſhall make appear to you, whether</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Fear,</hi> we underſtand only the Natural Paſſion of Fear, as it has ſomething dreadful, whether Perſon or thing, for its Object.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or whether by <hi>Fear</hi> we underſtand all that Duty and Obedience of which <hi>Fear</hi> is a proper &amp; efficacious Principle.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If by fear we underſtand that natural Paſſion, which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45788:15"/> has ſomething dreadful for its Object, even in this ſenſe God is to be feared more than Kings. For the Reaſon of all Fear is a Power to hurt and annoy, to aflict and torment us, and our Fears of any Object encreaſe proportionably to the Meaſures and Degrees of Power, which we conceive to be in it. Now God upon this account muſt neceſſarily be the Supreme Principal Object of our Fear, becauſe He only is Omnipotent and has Power to puniſh and undo us, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beyond what Kings can inflict, but infinitly beyond what the united force and ſtrength of the whole Creation can reach unto. And therefore Kings and Princes, who may think themſelves ſo ſecure as not to fear man, have yet reaſon in Common with all their Subjects to fear God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are no leſs ſubject to his Power, nor leſs accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to his Juſtice than the meaneſt man upon Earth. And accordingly it is the Pſalmiſt's Advice unto them, <hi>Be wiſe now therefore O ye King, be learned ye that are Judges of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>Earth, ſerve the Lord in fear, and Rejoice unto him with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence.</hi> So that God is terrible to thoſe who are terrible to others, and juſtly expects that even Kings, who are fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and honoured by their own Subjects, ſhould pay Him the Homage of their Fear, and the Tribute of their Reverence, But there could be no ground for this, except God exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Kings in Force &amp; Power and had Strength to ſubdue and chaſtiſe them, and to make them feel the Effects of his Wrath whenſoever they ſhould Violate the Laws of His Government.</p>
            <p>And therefore, if ever it ſhould fall out, that God &amp; Kings ſhould be Competitors for our Fear, by requiring contrary and repugnant Duties, ſo that in ſuch Circumſtances we
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45788:15"/> could not fear the One, without deſpiſing the Other, Our Bleſſed Saviour has plainly reſolved the Caſe by bidding us <hi>not to fear thoſe, who only can kill the Body but to fear</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10 18.</note> 
               <hi>him who after he hath Kill'd hath power to deſtroy both body and Soul in Hell.</hi> And the reaſon upon which our Bleſſed Saviour determins the ſuppoſed Caſe, is ſuch as can never be anſwered; for it is taken from the vaſt difference and infinite inequality, which is betwixt the reſpective Powers of God and man who contend for our fear. For he ſhews Us that the greateſt Kings and Potentates can only deſtroy the frail periſhing part of us, our Bodies; &amp; when they have done that, there's an end of their Power, they can do no more; but God can not only do that, but infinirely more; He can kill our Bodies, and after that deſtroy both Body and Soul in Hell.</p>
            <p>Let the Conſideration of this then awaken our fear of God and affect our Minds with ſuch a ſenſible dread of his Almighty Being, which no threatnings or Perſecutions of evil men for the cauſe of Our Holy Religion ſhall ever be able to Obliterate or Extinguiſh. For as ſuch fear is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely reaſonable, ſo it is infinitly neceſſary. For our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience will alwayes follow our feares, and we ſhall adhere to the Cauſe of God and perſevere in our faithfulneſs to him according to the awful conceipts and apprehenſions, which we bear in our minds of his Infinite and Irreſiſtible Power. For if we fear man more than God, it will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be in the Power of man to make us Apoſtates, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters and to Bowdown to any thing which they ſhall ſet up for the Object of our Religious Worſhip. But if we fear God above man, no human threatning, no worldly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45788:16"/> Terrors will be able to make any ſinful impreſſions upon us, nor ever prevail with us to make ſhipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience, and both theſe we ought to keep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and inviolate in deſpight of all the allurements and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of this World to the contrary. For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. If by Fear we underſtand all that Duty and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of which fear is a proper and efficacious Principle, then in this ſenſe alſo we ought to fear God more then Kings. For Obedience has relation to Authority, and the Obligations to its performance proceed intirely from their Commands, who have Authority to determine and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Inſtances of it. And nothing can be more plain than that the higheſt Authority muſt create the higheſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to Obedience, which are impoſſible to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd or weakned by any inferiour and ſubordinate Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Now God is the Supream Sovereign Lord of the whole Univerſe, the Fountain and Original of all that juſt and Lawful Authority which is exercis'd in it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as Kings have no Authority but what they have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from God, ſo they can have none againſt him, none but what is ſubordinate to His, and which no further Obligeth, than as the expreſſes of it are conſiſtent with thoſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Will. So that all the Powers of the World cannot abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate or cancel the Laws of Heaven, nor diſcharge mankind from that Duty and Service, to which they direct them. For to ſuppoſe otherwiſe is to ſuppoſe, that Kings do not Reign by God, but that God Reigns by Kings, that Kings are not Gods Miniſters, the ſubordinate Inſtruments and Deputies of his Providence but are Inveſted with a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount Power, with an Infinite, Boundleſs Unacountable
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45788:16"/> Jurisdiction not only in reſpect of their own Subjects, but alſo of God himſelf. But what is this but to diveſt God of his Legiſlative Power, to Pull him out of his Throne, and wreſt his Scepter out of his hands, and to make Kings Gods in the higheſt Senſe and moſt abſolute Notion of the Word? for this muſt needs be ſo, If Gods Authority be ſo precarious as to depend upon the wills of Princes for its Obliging Power and Vertue. But this is ſo fooliſh and blaſphemous a Conceit, that nothing but the mention of it is neceſſary for its Confutation. And therefore tho' it is an Infinit Mercy when Kings are Nurſing Fathers and Queens Nurſing Mothers to the Church, when the true Religion is encourag'd and protected by the Civil Powers of the World, and the Doctrine of the Goſpel are adopted and incorporated into the Laws of the Kingdom, yet if ever it ſhould happen that Kings ſhould command what God hath forbidden, or forbid what God has Commanded &amp; that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſevereſt Penalties which are poſſible for them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive and inflict, it vvould be both our Duty and our Intereſt to perſiſt in our Chriſtian profeſſion, and to ſuffer all the Torments, which Human Nature is capable of feeling, rather then Violate the unalterable Laws of God by any ſinful Compliances with the unlawful Impoſitions of Man. For the Nature of ſaving Truth and the fixed Methods of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation depend not upon the will of Man but of God, who only has Dominion over our Conſciences, and will bring us to Eternal Bliſs only in the way of his own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment. And therefore whenſoever the Commands of Men ſhall thwart and contradict the Lavvs of God, let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that in ſuch caſes (as vve value the Eternal happineſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45788:17"/> of our immortal Souls) we muſt obey God rather than Man: But then we muſt remember too, that as in ſuch Caſes it is the Will of God, that we ſhould not obey the Commands of men, ſo it is alſo His Will that we ſhould not reſiſt their Authority, nor riſe up in Rebellion againſt them. For the Power of the Sword, both by the Laws of God and Man, is the Sovereign's peculiar Right, and no man can make uſe of it without His Command, or againſt His Authority, without making himſelf Obnoxious both to Humane, and Divine Vengeance. And therefore in all Caſes where we cannot obey the Laws of Man, without offending God, we muſt patiently ſuffer their Wrath, and meekly ſubmit to their Coercion.</p>
            <p>This is the Doctrine of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, and this is the Doctrine of the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> which She has reaſon to Glory in beyond all other Churches of what Denomination ſoever, becauſe none beſide Her ſelf (which I know of) do Teach the Doctrine of Non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and Paſſive Obedience ſo plainly and fully, ſo free from all Ambiguities and Reſerves, from all Exceptions and Limitations. May we all Adorn our excellent Church, by living conformably to Her holy Doctrine in all things, and then I am ſure we ſhall Convince the World, that we both Fear God and the King, by giving <hi>unto God the things that are Gods,</hi> and <hi>unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſar</hi>'s.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45788:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
